Guide to the Architecture Collection 1873-2016
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Architecture collection
1873-2016
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 1525
Oregon Historical Society
3 cubic feet 5 document cases, 3 oversize folders
Collection assembled by the Oregon Historical Society primarily containing ephemera relating to architecture in Oregon, with emphasis on Portland. Includes brochures on specific buildings, booklets of sample house plans, and historical background on the Paulina Lake (Or.) I.O.O.F. site.
Historical note
Since its founding in 1898, the Oregon Historical Society has collected ephemera of all kinds, most of it documenting the history of Oregon and the Pacific Northwest. In the mid-20th century, librarians at the Society began organizing these materials into what became known as "Topical Collections." One such collection, the Architecture Collection, collated various items concerning buildings, architects, and related matters.
The Architecture Collection contains primarily ephemera related to individual buildings, most of them in Portland. These materials include brochures created either for sales promotion or for dedications of the finished structures. Also included are materials relating to architectural firms and organizations, historic preservation, building materials, sample plans for houses, and architecture-related events. There is a large group of materials on the history of the Odd Fellows (I.O.O.F.) camp site at Paulina Lake, Oregon; and publicity for Pioneer Courthouse Square in Portland. The collection also contains blueprints for ferry boats crossing the Columbia River at Astoria, 1947, designed by the Albina Engine and Machine Works; and blueprints for railroad cars, 1891-1928.
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series A: Building files
Series B: General files
The collection is open to the public.
The collection was assembled from various sources by the Oregon Historical Society
Materials are added to the collection from time to time.
The Oregon Historical Society holds a significant collection of blueprints and scale drawings of structures throughout Oregon, including designs from the firms of Pietro Belluschi, Morris Whitehouse, A. E. Doyle, Claussen & Claussen, and Jamieson Parker.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
International Order of Odd Fellows.
Oregon--Buildings, structure, etc.; Paulina Lake (Or.)--Buildings, structure, etc.; Pioneer Courthouse Square (Portland, Or.); Portland (Or.)--Buildings, structure, etc.
Architecture--Oregon; Architects--Oregon
Oregon; Portland; City and Town Life; Architecture; Architectural Drawings
Printed ephemera; Architectural drawings (visual works)
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Buildings, 1873-2009; Series A
  All buildings are in Portland, Oregon and vicinity, unless otherwise noted
  - Apartments and condominiums, circa 1970-2000 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Commercial buildings, A-L, circa 1910-2000 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Includes:
    Centennial Block remodel, circa 1990
    Emanuel Hospital Medical Building, circa 1970
    Equitable Center, circa 1965
    Fleisher Building, 1946
    Henry Building, circa 1910
    Hilton Hotel, circa 1963
  - Commercial buildings, M-Z, circa 1926-2009 (Box-folder 1/3)
    Pacific Building, 1926
    Postal Building remodel, circa 1984
    Princeton Building (formerly Elks Temple), 1985
    Rocky Butte Jail
    Studio Building, circa 1927
  - Eliot Tower, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - First National Center, circa 1972 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Justice Center, 1984 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - KOIN Center (Fountain Place), circa 1984 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Ladd Tower, 2006 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Mount Angel Abbey Library (designed by Alvar Aalto)--Dedication program, 1970 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - New Market Colonnade (copy of drawing of proposed structure), undated (Box-folder Oversize folder 3)
  - New Market Theater remodel, 1983 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Non-Portland Buildings, 1938-1986; undated (Box-folder 2/3)
  - One, Pacific Square, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Oregon Historical Society building-- Architecture/West article, 1967 July (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Oregon State Capitol, Salem, 1873-1988; undated (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Pacwest Center, 1983 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Pioneer Courthouse renovation, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Pioneer Courthouse Square (including design competition), circa 1980-1990 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Pioneer Courthouse Square--Fundraising brochure, circa 1983 (Box-folder Oversize folder 3)
  - Portland Building (designed by Michael Graves), circa 1981-1982 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Portland Historic Landmarks Commission, 1977-1985 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Portland Performing Arts Center (including Arlene Schnitzer Concert Hall), circa 1980-1990 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Portland Place (future Pioneer Place)--Prospectus, 1983 (Box-folder Oversize folder 3)
  - Standard Plaza (Standard Insurance Company), circa 1970-1980 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Street of Dreams (residential showcases), 1983-1997 (Box-folder 3/3-3/4)
  - Vista House Taskforce (Columbia Gorge), 1982 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Washington Square (shopping mall), undated (Box-folder Oversize folder 3)
- General Files, 1894-2008; Series B
  - American Institute of Architects, general, 1964-1999; undated (Box-folder 4/1)
  - American Institute of Architects--Meeting minutes, 1968-1979 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - American Society for Metals, Oregon Chapter--Rosters, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Architects and architectural firms, 1894-2012 (Box-folder 4/4)
    Includes Henneberry Eddy brochure, circa 2012
  - Builders and remodelers, 1985; undate (Box-folder 4/5)
    See also Business Collection, Mss 1510.
  - Building directories, Portland, undated (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Building materials, 1913-1982 (Box-folder 4/7)
    See also Business Collection, Mss 1510
  - Demonstration homes for 1938: especially prepared for low income families (plans for small houses) (Box-folder Oversize folder 3)
  - Estratto da l'architettura: cronache e storia (Italian architecture magazine with artilce on Zimmer, Gunsul Frasca firm of Portland), circa 1968 (Box-folder Oversize folder 3)
  - Events--Building dedication invitations and programs, 1917-2005 (Box-folder 4/8-4/9)
    Includes programs for dedication of the Portland Public Auditorium, 1917; U.S. Courthouse, 1994
  - Events--Exhibitions and other programs, 1909-2000 (Box-folder 4/9)
    Includes program for Portland Architectural Club, second annual exhibition, 1909
  - "Factors of value on new buildings" by Hiram U. Welch--Booklet on assessment of Portland buildings, with pictures and data on various houses and buildings, 1926 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - "Fallout protection for homes with basements" (pamphlet), U.S. Office of Civil Defense, 1967 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Historic Preservation League of Oregon, circa 1980-1990 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Historic properties, 1955-2008; undated (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Laurelhurst and its Park (original publication and facsimile edition, Laurelhurst subdivision, Portland), 1916; undated (Box-folder Oversize folder 3)
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation--Brochures, newsletter, 1956-1980 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Paulina Lake I.O.O.F. site--History and preservation projects, 1960-1982 (Box-folder 5/5-5/9)
    Papers include history of the leasing and use of the site and construction of the lodge, written by Oscar Larson, Past Noble Grand of Bend Lodge, I.O.O.F.; "Assesment of Log Cabins and Lodge on Paulina Lake, Deschutes National Forest," by Mazama Conservation Committee, 1980; "Addendum to Evaluation Report" on site and structures by E. Gail Throop, Forest Service historian, 1981; affidavit of Palmer Byrkit, evaluating the lodge and cabins, 1982, for Paulina Lake Historic Cabin Owners Association v. U.S.D.A. Forest Service; and complaint and motion for preliminary injunction, 1982, for Paulina Lake Historical Cabin Owners Association v. U.S.D.A. Forest Service. See also Org. Lot 526, Oregon Historical Society Research Library, for photographs.
  - Plans and scale drawings
    - Farm buildings (Mid-West Farm Building Plan Service, University of Wisconsin), circa 1938 (Box-folder 5/10)
    - Ferry boats, 1947 (Box-folder Oversize Folder 1)
      Blueprints for ferry boats used on the Columbia River at Astoria, constructed by the Albina Engine and Machine Works.
    - Railroad cars, 1881-1928 (Box-folder Oversize Folder 2)
      Blueprints for railroad cars. Includes:
      New York Central and Hudson River car, side view, 1891
      Southern Pacific coach, 1927
      Southern Pacific club car, 1922
      Southern Pacific locomotive, 1922
      Southern Pacific diner, 1925
      Southern Pacific observation car, circa 1914
      Southern Pacific water tanker, undated
    - Residential, circa 1920-1980 (Box-folder 5/11)
      Includes "100 modern home plans selected for building economy" by Residential Plan Service, Portland, 1957. See also Business Collection, Mss 1510.
  - Propery sales, residential, 1998-2005 (Box-folder 5/12)
  - Public art, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 5/13)
  - Residential design-- "Atomic Ranch", circa 2007 (Box-folder 5/14)
  - Residential design-- Green & solar homes of Oregon, 2003 (Box-folder 5/15)
  - Society of Architectural Historians, circa 1970-1990 (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Uban planning and design, 1979-1987 (Box-folder 5/17)
  - Walking tours of Portland, 1976-1992; undated (Box-folder 5/18)